<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>What is Miklos hacking - Tags: upc</title>
        <description></description>
        <link>http://vmiklos.hu/blog/</link>
        <item>
            <title>UPC vs port forwarding</title>
            <description>&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UPC_Broadband"&gt;UPC&lt;/a&gt; traditionally had a setup
consisting of a cable modem providing internet access to a single computer,
and then it was up to the users if they use that access to really connect to a
computer or to a router, providing wireless access and so on.  It seems, these
days they are more after actually &lt;em&gt;encouraging&lt;/em&gt; people to use their
subscription on multiple devices&amp;#8201;&amp;#8212;&amp;#8201;possibly that way it&amp;#8217;s easier to sell
larger packages (like 60 MBit/s download rate instead of 30 MBit/s, etc).  One
fallout from this move is that they started to replace modems with a
combination of modems and routers, in this case this is an
&lt;a href="http://www.ubeeinteractive.com/products/cable/evw3226"&gt;Ubee EVW3226&lt;/a&gt;, with the
brand removed. I wanted to try out if this new device could replace my
previous router or not&amp;#8201;&amp;#8212;&amp;#8201;so far it seems to be good enough, though there was
one pitfall, hence this post.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s possible to define a range of IP addresses to be used for DHCP purposes,
though you can&amp;#8217;t serve fixed IP addresses based on the MAC address of the
clients. Given that my home network isn&amp;#8217;t that large, I can tolerate that: as
long as there is a range that can be safely used for fixed addresses, I can
configure that manually.  It&amp;#8217;s also possible to do port forwarding, e.g.
redirecting the incoming ssh traffic to a given address&amp;#8201;&amp;#8212;&amp;#8201;except you can&amp;#8217;t do
both at the same time: you can&amp;#8217;t redirect traffic to an address that&amp;#8217;s not
known (served via DHCP) to the router. Which is a shame, the #1 use case for
port forwarding is to redirect traffic to a home-server that will then also
have a fixed IP internally&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="paragraph"&gt;&lt;p&gt;So here is a hack that allowed me to still do this: set the start of the range
of the DHCP served IP&amp;#8217;s exactly to the address of the (to be used in future
as) fixed address, e.g. 192.168.0.5. Connect with one client, so that the
address will be &lt;em&gt;known&lt;/em&gt; to the router. Then add the port-forwarding rule,
finally set the DHCP range back to its original value (in my case I use
192.168.0.1..99 for fixed addresses and 100+ for dynamic purposes). It&amp;#8217;s a
stupid trick, but it works&amp;#8230; ;-)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <link>http://vmiklos.hu/blog/upc-port-forward.html</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2014 20:56:33 +0200</pubDate>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">http://vmiklos.hu/blog/upc-port-forward.html</guid>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
